<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on {{Ramesh  Ponnada}}</title>
    <link>http://rameshponnada.in/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on {{Ramesh  Ponnada}}</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Jun 2018 08:46:57 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://rameshponnada.in/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>12 Factor Applications for Cloud Native</title>
      <link>http://rameshponnada.in/2018/06/24/12-factor-applications-for-cloud-native/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jun 2018 08:46:57 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rameshponnada.in/2018/06/24/12-factor-applications-for-cloud-native/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The world in your pocket</title>
      <link>http://rameshponnada.in/2017/04/04/the-world-in-your-pocket/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2017 10:46:57 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rameshponnada.in/2017/04/04/the-world-in-your-pocket/</guid>
      <description>Google Maps has gone from location finder to daily travel companion, and India has played a part in its development, says Sanket Gupta, Program Manager, Google Maps
Eight years ago, when I moved to Chennai for college, a relative suggested I get myself a map of the new, unfamiliar city. An actual, physical map. In 2009, this did not seem an outlandish suggestion, as it would take me a while to figure out the many bakkams, konams, pets and pettahs that were interspersed around the city.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cyber attacks getting hi-tech</title>
      <link>http://rameshponnada.in/2017/04/04/cyber-attacks-getting-hi-tech/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2017 08:46:57 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rameshponnada.in/2017/04/04/cyber-attacks-getting-hi-tech/</guid>
      <description>There is now hardly any difference between run-of-the-mill attacks and State-sponsored ones, say security experts
One of the oldest methods of online attacks is breaking into someone’s email. The reports during last year’s US Presidential elections that hackers had stolen e-mails from John Podesta, the chairman of Hillary Clinton’s campaign, reminded everyone how vulnerable e-mails still are.
While targets have remained the same, what has evolved over years are techniques adopted by criminals to mask their trail and thereby make it difficult to investigate and find solutions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Engineering the markets where users are</title>
      <link>http://rameshponnada.in/2017/04/04/engineering-the-markets-where-users-are/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2017 08:46:57 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rameshponnada.in/2017/04/04/engineering-the-markets-where-users-are/</guid>
      <description>The spectrum of design work in the context of web and mobile is very wide. Front-end engineering has emerged as a challenging job role in this backdrop, as engineers must combine combine design and User Interface (UI) engineering skills. These skills could be inherent, or they must be acquired on the ‘job’. Design schools are far behind in producing front-end engineers, because the pedagogy paradigm in these institutions does not consider, let alone include, code as a way to produce repeatable elements of interface design.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Samsung launches flagship Galaxy S8, S8 Plus</title>
      <link>http://rameshponnada.in/2017/04/04/samsung-launches-flagship-galaxy-s8-s8-plus/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2017 08:46:57 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rameshponnada.in/2017/04/04/samsung-launches-flagship-galaxy-s8-s8-plus/</guid>
      <description>Samsung also revealed Bixby, a smart voice assistant to rival Apple’s Siri and Google’s Assistant
After much speculation over its built and specifications over past few months, South Korean giant Samsung on Wednesday launched its flagship device, Galaxy S8, that has a voice assistant.
The device comes in two variants with different screen sizes — the 5.8-inch Galaxy S8 and 6.2-inch Galaxy S8 Plus — and will be available from April 21.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Twitter eases 140-character limit in replies</title>
      <link>http://rameshponnada.in/2017/04/04/twitter-eases-140-character-limit-in-replies/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2017 08:46:57 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rameshponnada.in/2017/04/04/twitter-eases-140-character-limit-in-replies/</guid>
      <description>Twitter has found more creative ways to ease its 140-character limit without officially raising it.
Now, the company says that when you reply to someone or to a group usernames will no longer count toward those 140 characters. This will be especially helpful with group conversations, where replying to two, three or more users at a time could be especially difficult with the character constraints.
When users reply, the names of the people they are replying to will be on top of the text of the actual tweet, rather than a part of it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>WhatsApp: The most secure app for making video calls?</title>
      <link>http://rameshponnada.in/2017/04/04/whatsapp-the-most-secure-app-for-making-video-calls/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2017 08:46:57 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rameshponnada.in/2017/04/04/whatsapp-the-most-secure-app-for-making-video-calls/</guid>
      <description>WhatsApp already has end-to-end encryption and has said the same would apply to its video-calling feature.
WhatsApp on Tuesday rolled out its video calling feature in a phased manner to over a billion users around the world across multiple platforms (iphone, Android and Windows).
WhatsApp, which currently offers messaging, group chats and voice calling services is hugely popular in India, with over 150 million active users.
In a blog post, the company announced that it was committed to making quality video “available to everyone, not just those who can afford the most expensive new phones or live in countries with the best cellular networks.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>